I think I figured out a way to plan any
size of work with an agent. The existing
planning tools that I was using and
playing around with, even ones that I've
created, felt too constrained, too tied
to a single session. I felt like I
wasn't able to be ambitious enough, and
because of that, I was kind of
constraining the stuff I was building to
fit AI, which doesn't feel right. This
new approach doesn't have that limit.
You can plan enormous chunks of work,
and it will orchestrate the planning
over multiple types of sessions. It
knows that you can't make your way
cleanly to the destination. You have to
clear the fog of war. It understands
dependent decisions, and it even allows
you to plan in parallel. And the best
thing about this is this is based on
software fundamentals. This is based on
the fundamentals of planning work that I
learned when I was a real developer
before AI. And I've packaged this all up
into a skill that's available right now
on my skills repo called Wayfinder. So,
the way that I was planning work before
was really tied into a single session.
It's to do with the grill me or the
grill with doc skill that's in my skills
repo. That's still a super important
primitive, but it's really just tied
into a single session. Some work is
bigger than what you can fit into the
context window, and especially the smart
zone of the context window of the agent.
And you know that going in, so you'll
often take time ahead of these AI agent
sessions to break it down into smaller
chunks, say, "Oh, I'll just bite off
this little bit. I'll just bite off this
little bit." But then what you'll find
is, "Okay, I'm working towards planning
in this bit of grilling." And then you
reach a question that you can't answer,
or you just find yourself lost in fog.
And all the time you're managing the
smart zone, you're trying not to spend
too many tokens. This has been out there
for a while, and people are freaking
loving this thing. It one-shotted a
prototype, it kept starting again and
again for months. I really hate the
phrase one-shotting, but I think what he
means is it really helped him out. John
here even built his own freaking harness
because he liked the wayfinder approach
so much. It's got these gorgeous little
star map on it that kind of lets you
take tasks as you go. So, it's been out
there for a little while and I'm finally
making the video that people want me to
make. What is wayfinder? How do you best
use it? Well, let's start by looking at
how big work typically gets planned. You
have a start point, a point where you
need to start from, a sort of vague
idea, not really how to get there. And
you're trying to get to some kind of
destination. You know vaguely where you
want to end up, but the steps between
are super foggy. You've no idea how to
get. This is true, by the way, in
engineering, but it's also true in many
walks of life where you're planning
something ambitious. And so, the first
thing you should probably do is have a
grilling session about it. Get the AI to
interview you and figure out the sort of
basic premise of where you're going.
Now, for some work, that's sufficient
and you'll be able to get straight to
your destination. But for a lot of work,
that will still leave you in a lot of
fog. What you might find is based on
that initial grilling session, you need
to do more sessions. So, you might have
a prototyping session, or you might have
another grilling session, or it might
need to go off and do some research as
well. Conceptually, what we're looking
at here is a map. We are creating a map
of how we're getting to our destination.
This is why it's called wayfinder. We
are finding our way to the destination.
And each of these things on the map,
they are tickets. Each ticket requires
its own individual session with the
agents. So, you might have a prototyping
session, a grilling session, and a
research session. And all of those
things are created and managed by
wayfinder. And just a note here, yeah,
this is just a single skill doing all
this and it works with any coding agent.
On its map, wayfinder gives you a
frontier of tickets here. In other
words, the decisions that it knows about
so far. And it also keeps track of
everything that's in fog. So, things
that are not quite able to be decided
upon yet because we haven't done the
research, or we don't have a prototype
to look at, or we haven't done enough
conversation, enough grilling. At some
point, all of the fog will be resolved,
and then you'll have finally made enough
decisions to finally get to your
destination. Wayfinder can not only
manage the research, but it could also
do tasks here, too. So, if you need to
set up some configuration, or you need
to go out and talk to someone, and
actually go and run an errand, then
Wayfinder can figure that out for you,
as well. In other words, all of the
complicated stuff that you might need to
do while you're planning something big,
Wayfinder orchestrates it all for you.
It keeps track of everything that's been
done, and it measures the fog of war for
you, keeps track of all the frontier of
things you can decide right now. How
does it keep track of it? Well, it does
it in your issue tracker. In my public
course video manager repo, here are all
of the Wayfinder maps that I've done
recently. And you notice that if we look
at this one, there are This is the big
old map here, and underneath it are 12
subtasks, or sub-issues, and these are
the decision tickets. So, we can zoom
down here, and we can understand all of
the decisions that have been made. As
decisions get made, then obviously, they
get resolved inside the ticket. So, in
this one, this is a sub-issue, close the
clips during publish race, and we
resolved it with a discussion a couple
of weeks ago. That resolution also gets
written back up to the parent map. So,
if we look back up here, we can see that
a small version of that also gets
written in the map. Wayfinder is keeping
track of all the decisions that have
been made, all the prototypes that have
been created, all the tasks that have
been done. And by the way, even though
I'm using GitHub for this, my skills are
issue tracker agnostic. So, you can use
it with any issue tracker you like. You
just need to do a little bit of
configuration via
setup.mappercode.skills. Use it with
Linear, use it with Jira, use it with
literally whatever you like. The very
first thing you'll need to decide when
you kick off a new Wayfinder session is
the destination. For instance, in this
one, I was adding a command palette with
a bunch of new actions into my
application. And what I ended up wanting
was a buildable spec. So, I wanted a
specification for this command K command
palette in the CVM diagram window. So, I
started it off like this. I invoked the
Wayfinder skill, and then I gave it a
description of what I wanted. I'd like
the ability in the CVM to add an icon
picker. Not only that, I want the
ability to search other diagrams. I want
the ability to copy things from the
diagram and save them as, you know, big
old chunk of work. It went through and
explored the repo, and it invoked the
grilling skill, and it grilled me about
what I wanted. It first asked me what
done looks like, whether I wanted a
spec, and it recommended a spec. That's
good. And then it asked me a few initial
questions before then going and creating
some tickets and the first map. And it
created the other tickets as sub-issues.
So, we kicked off with seven tickets
immediately. However, only three of
those tickets were takable right now.
So, figure out where icon names come
from, component storage schema, and
palette information architecture and
grid keyboard. I don't remember that
one. And so, what I did was I then
worked through each of those tickets in
a new session. The way I did that was I
just called Wayfinder on that ticket
name. I did it in a slightly fancier way
where I actually have a handoff skill
that automatically wrote me a prompt and
spawned a Claude sub-agent. But what it
was essentially doing is just calling
the Wayfinder skill on this map and on
the specific ticket, wherever it was.
Yeah, here it is. Here's your ticket.
Translucent SVG geometry to path
builder. And it just mentions the full
ticket name. So, this is how you work
through a Wayfinder map. You do an
initial Wayfinder prompt just to chart
the map and figure out the next tickets.
And then for each ticket, you say
Wayfinder with the ticket URL. So, you
use Wayfinder for both, both for
charting the map initially and then
walking through each ticket. As you can
probably see from this diagram, tickets
can have different types, and there are
four types. And these ticket types are
actually brought into the issue tracker
themselves. So, we actually have
Wayfinder research, which is a ticket
type. Research tickets are where the
agent needs to go off and find some
information and bring it back. And it
usually kicks it off immediately. So,
you don't actually need to watch it. It
does it in a sub agent and then reports
back. Prototype tickets, which are the
next type here, create a prototype,
which is so unbelievably in valuable for
really seeing things come to life as
you're planning. I've done a whole extra
video on this, on how important
prototypes are, and it reuses the
prototype skill from that video. Some
folks look at Wayfinder, and they think,
"God, that's a lot of planning. Doesn't
that look like waterfall?" And the
prototypes are the way that you prevent
it from becoming waterfall, huge amounts
of low-fidelity upfront planning. A
prototype is a high-fidelity way to get
feedback on what you're actually
building. And the fact that Wayfinder
encourages you to build so many
prototypes means that the output is
unbelievably good. So, so far, we've got
research, prototype. Obviously, there
are grilling ones as well. So, grilling
sessions. And this is just where you
need a discussion over maybe an
implementation detail, over a particular
aspect of the plan. And the final type
of ticket are tasks. These are things
that need to be done in the real world,
stuff that the agent can't quite do
itself, or possibly sometimes the stuff
agent can do itself, but is scheduled
behind other work. One really cool thing
about Wayfinder is the way that it
establishes blocking relationships
between tickets, because some decisions
can only be made once other decisions
are made. And so, what you end up with
is here, we've got 14 out of 17 done on
this map. So, a lot of work done, but
we've still not built the skill that
this whole map is built around. And once
we build the skill, then we actually
need to revisit some other stuff based
on how the skill works and how it
actually improves things. And And what
you're doing a lot of the time when
you're working through a Wayfinder map
is going, "Okay, I've resolved that
ticket. Let's see how this opens up new
tickets. What has the frontier moved
to?" So, then once the map is complete,
what do you then go and do with it?
Well, this one, because its detonation
was a spec, the Wayfinder map is
probably a little bit too dense to
create a spec. So, what I like to do is
create a spec from the map. This was the
spec that I created from it, and you can
see it's basically the same setup as
I've had before. I literally just called
to spec on the Wayfinder map, and it
pulled in this enormous
document with basically all of the
decisions that have been pulled from the
Wayfinder map into this GitHub issue.
The initial draft was actually too large
for GitHub's character limit, so
>> [laughter]
>> that kind of tells you how big it was.
And from there, I turned it into tickets
using my usual approach, which is to
spec and then to tickets. In other
words, Wayfinder fits in just in exactly
the same place that Grill with Docs does
in my usual approach. So, instead of
doing Grill with Docs and then doing to
spec into tickets, you're spending a lot
more time in Wayfinder creating this
enormous map, and then taking that map,
turning it to spec, turning it to
tickets, and then implementing each
ticket, and then running code review at
the end. The really cool thing about the
Wayfinder setup is that the specs that
it creates are so dense, and they all
link back to the original decision
tickets. So, you can actually go, and
the agent can go and view the primary
source if it's confused about anything.
That was always a kind of weakness with
Grill with Docs, which is that you were
really relying on the spec to be the
source of truth, but the spec is always
just a summary of what was actually said
in the meeting. Whereas now, with
Wayfinder, you've actually got access to
that primary source, which is amazing.
So, that is Wayfinder. It's a way of
mapping huge chunks of work by planning
things out really in detail ahead of
time. It can handle prototyping, can
handle research, can handle arbitrary
tasks, can handle discussions, too.
Let's jump into an FAQ now of frequently
asked questions that I get when people
ask me about Wayfinder. The first one is
"This is way too much process. This way
too heavy for the kind of work that I
do. When should I actually use it?"
Well, the answer to this is if you think
the work that you're doing can be
completable and planable in a single
session, then plan it in a single
session. If you kind of already know the
way to your destination, then there's no
need to use Wayfinder because you can
just path your way there in a single
session and just figure it out.
Wayfinder is for the cases where you
have the fog of war. You'll no idea
quite where to go and you just need to
start and then see where you get to. By
the way, I've actually been using
Wayfinder for non-coding tasks. So, I've
been meaning to put up a garden office
in my garden and I've been using
Wayfinder for that. So, it's
commissioning a site survey, figuring
out all that stuff, figuring out who to
contact, doing all the research, finding
the different firms that could build it.
It's awesome. Another response people
have to Wayfinder is this is SDD. This
is spectrum development and I don't want
to do spectrum development. I don't want
to spend all this time putting together
a spec. This seems bananas. Well, the
way I think of specs is really just a
destination for a multi-session piece of
work. In other words, we have a huge
task down here, let's say task number
four, that we're trying to schedule over
multiple agent sessions cuz it's just
too big. And what we want to do is we
need a spec so that we can when we get
to the end figure out where we were
going. That's all a spec is in this
context. It's just a destination
document to handle this multi-session
work. And then each session is done in
an implementation ticket. Also, this is
people get confused when they first use
Wayfinder cuz they go, "Right, it's
creating some tickets. Aren't we
supposed to do the tickets later?" These
are kind of implementation tickets
versus decision tickets. So, in
Wayfinder you have decision tickets.
These are implementation tickets. So,
the difference between my approach and
most other approaches is that people,
when they get to the end of this, they
will keep that spec around somewhere.
For me, I close the issue containing the
spec, and the spec is gone. It's gone
from my repository. I rarely, if ever,
refer to it again. Once the spec is
present in the code, then you can just
delete the spec. Whereas, people who do
spec-driven development go back to the
spec and edit it and modify it. There
are lots of approaches to spectrum
development, so I'm probably annoying
someone with that, but what I'm
essentially trying to say is that these
specs are non-persistent. With that,
folks, I recommend you go off and you
chart your own awesome foggy idea. I
have found Wayfinder just so liberating
in that it just lets me get started, and
it handles all of that difficult
decision for me. I've been using it to
plan courses, been using it to do
engineering work, been using it to build
a garden office. It is just awesome. The
cool thing about it is that the
destination is totally up to you.
Whether you want it to create a spec
that you then run through an AFK agent,
which is what I do, or if you just want
to it to implement the work for you in
tasks, then it totally can. There is no
more fun feeling than starting a new
Wayfinder session, and knowing that
you're going to see something awesome,
but not quite knowing how you're going
to get there. If you're into this stuff,
and if you want to keep up with my
skills, then you should check out this
seven-lesson free course that I've put
out on AI skills for real engineers,
which is on my AI Hero site. I'll add
the link below. This lets you build up a
repeatable workflow that you can ship
great work, and it's all built on solid
software fundamentals. Thanks so much
for hanging out. It is always fun
filming these sessions, and I'm so glad
that people are enjoying Wayfinder so
much. So, cheers, pals. I will see you
in the next one.